Williams Obstetrics.
Chapter 44: Management of Obstetrical Hemorrhage.
Management Of Hemorrhage Blood Replacement Obstetrical Coagulopathies Surgical Management Of Hemorrhage References Recognition of obstetrical hemorrhage severity is crucial to its management.
However, visual estimates, especially when blood losses are excessive, are notoriously inaccurate.
In many cases, true volume losses are often two to three times the clinical estimate.
Moreover, in obstetrics, part and sometimes even all of the lost blood may be concealed.
Estimation is further complicated in that peripartum hemorrhage also includes the pregnancyaugmented blood volume.
After pregnancy hypervolemia is lost at delivery, blood loss can be estimated by calculating 500 mL loss for each 3 volume percent drop in hematocrit.
Its nadir depends on the speed of resuscitation with intravenous crystalloids and blood products.
With ongoing blood loss, the real-time hematocrit is at its maximum whenever measured in the delivery, operating, or recovery room.
Prudently, if blood loss is considered more than average, the hematocrit is determined, and plans are made for close observation for potential physiological deterioration.
Blood loss determination as recommended by the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2019b) is discussed in detail in Chapter 42.
Urine output measured hourly is one of the most important “vital signs.
Unless diuretic agents are given—and these are seldom indicated with active bleeding—accurately measured urine flow reflects renal perfusion.
This in turn reflects perfusion of other vital organs.
The volume of urine output should be ≥30 mL/hr and preferably ≥50 mL/hr.
Another important factor to consider with management of hemorrhage is whether there are adequate procoagulants to achieve clot formation and stability.
Many cases of severe obstetrical hemorrhage are further complicated by disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC), in which blood has dysfunctional coagulation (p. 775).
Management Of Hemorrhage.
# Hypovolemic Shock.
Shock from hemorrhage evolves through several stages .
Early, the mean arterial pressure, stroke volume, cardiac output, central venous pressure, and pulmonary capillary wedge pressure decline.
Greater differences in arteriovenous oxygen content values reflect enhanced tissue oxygen extraction, although overall oxygen consumption falls.
Blood flow to capillary beds is controlled by arterioles, which are resistance vessels and partially controlled by the central nervous system (CNS).
However, approximately 70 percent of total blood volume is contained in venules, which are passive resistance vessels controlled by humoral factors.
Thus, the catecholamine release during hemorrhage prompts greater venular tone, and this provides an autotransfusion from this capacitance reservoir.
This volume boost is accompanied by compensatory rises in heart rate, systemic and pulmonary vascular resistance, and myocardial contractility.
At the same time, selective, CNS-mediated arteriolar constriction or relaxation, termed autoregulation, preferentially redistributes cardiac output and blood volume.
Thus, more blood flow is diverted to the heart, brain, and adrenal glands, whereas perfusion to the kidneys, splanchnic beds, muscles, skin, and uterus is relatively diminished.
When the blood volume deficit exceeds approximately 25 percent, compensatory mechanisms usually are inadequate to maintain cardiac output and blood pressure.
Importantly, additional small losses of blood will now cause rapid clinical deterioration.
Following an initial augmented total oxygen extraction by maternal tissue, maldistribution of blood flow results in local tissue hypoxia and metabolic acidosis.
This creates a vicious cycle of vasoconstriction, organ ischemia, and cellular death.
Hemorrhage also activates lymphocytes and monocytes, which in turn prompts endothelial cell activation and platelet aggregation .
This endotheliopathy promotes release of vasoactive mediators that occlude small vessels and further impair
microcirculatory perfusion.
Comorbid preeclampsia or sepsis also leads to loss of capillary endothelial integrity, additional loss of intravascular volume into the extracellular space, and platelet aggregation.
These then can incite DIC.
The pathophysiological events just described create important but often overlooked extracellular fluid and electrolyte shifts involved in both the genesis and successful treatment of hypovolemic shock.
These include changes in the cellular transport of various ions such as sodium and water into skeletal muscle as well as potassium loss.
Replacement of extracellular fluid and intravascular volume are both necessary.
Patient survival rates are enhanced in acute hemorrhagic shock if blood plus crystalloid solution are given compared with blood transfusions alone.
# Fluid Resuscitation.
Whenever excessive blood loss is suspected, steps are simultaneously taken to identify the bleeding source and to begin resuscitation.
Refer to the algorithm for hemorrhage management (Fig. 42-3, p. 735).
If the woman is undelivered, restoration of blood volume benefits both mother and fetus.
It also prepares for emergent delivery.
If she is postpartum, immediately identifying uterine atony, retained placental fragments, or genital tract lacerations is essential.
One or two large-bore intravenous infusion systems are ideally established promptly, crystalloid solutions are rapidly infused, and blood products are ordered.
An operating room is readied, and a surgical and anesthesia team are quickly assembled.
Specific management of hemorrhage is further dependent on its etiology.
A neonatal resuscitation team is included if imminent delivery is planned.
Serious hemorrhage demands prompt and adequate refilling of the intravascular compartment with crystalloid solutions.
These rapidly equilibrate into the extravascular space, and only 20 percent of crystalloid remains intravascular in critically ill patients after 1 hour .
Because of this, initial fluid is infused in a volume two to three times the estimated blood loss.
Crystalloid Versus Colloid Solutions Resuscitation of hypovolemic shock with colloid versus crystalloid solutions has been debated.
In a Cochrane review of resuscitation of nonpregnant critically ill patients, Lewis and coworkers (2018) found selection of colloids versus crystalloids probably makes little or no difference to mortality rates.
Similar results were found in the Saline versus Albumin Fluid Evaluation (SAFE) randomized trial of almost 7000 nonpregnant patients .
At Parkland Hospital, acute volume resuscitation is preferably done with crystalloid solutions and blood.
Either a saline-based or a balanced crystalloid solution may be infused.
The latter includes Ringer lactate and Plasma-Lyte solutions, which have electrolyte compositions similar to plasma.
In some studies, but not in all, balanced crystalloid solutions were found to be superior to saline-based ones (Semler, 2018; Yule, 2020).
Excessive saline-based crystalloid solution can theoretically lead to hyperchloremic acidosis.
In comparisons, the difficulty lies in separating the effects of the underlying pathophysiology driving the acidosis.
# Blood Replacement.
Type and Screen Versus Crossmatch A blood type and antibody screen should be performed for any woman at significant risk for hemorrhage.
Because prediction of women at risk for postpartum hemorrhage is poor, we perform type and screen in all women upon admission to labor and delivery.
Screening involves mixing maternal serum with standard reagent red cells that carry antigens to which most of the common clinically significant antibodies react.
Instead, crossmatching involves the use of actual donor erythrocytes rather than the standardized red cells.
This process is efficient, and only 0.03 to 0.07 percent of patients identified as having no antibodies are subsequently found to them .
Importantly, administration of screened blood rarely results in adverse clinical sequelae.
Transfusion Thresholds The hematocrit level or hemoglobin concentration threshold that mandates
blood transfusion is controversial .
Cardiac output does not substantively drop until the hemoglobin concentration falls to approximately 7 g/dL or when the hematocrit approximates 20 volume percent.
Military combat trauma units have used a target hematocrit of 21 volume percent, and at this level, most experts recommend consideration of red cell transfusion (Carson, 2017; Kogutt, 2019).
In general, with ongoing obstetrical hemorrhage, we recommend rapid blood infusion when the hematocrit is <25 volume percent.
Other decision-modifying factors are whether the fetus is undelivered; surgery is imminent or ongoing operative blood loss is expected; or maternal hypoxia, vascular collapse, or other factors are present.
Limited data address these issues.
In a study from the Canadian Critical Care Trials Group, nonpregnant patients were randomly assigned to restrictive red cell transfusions to maintain hemoglobin concentration >7 g/dL or to liberal transfusions to maintain the hemoglobin level at 10 to 12 g/dL.
The 30-day mortality rate was similar—19 versus 23 percent—in the restrictive versus liberal groups, respectively (Hébert, 1999).
Transfusion therapy in nonpregnant patients with septic shock had similar mortality rates when 7 g/dL was compared with 9 g/dL as targets for transfusions .
The number of units transfused in a given woman to reach a target hematocrit depends on her body mass and on the expectations of additional blood loss.
Blood Component Products The content and effects of transfusion of various blood components are shown in Table 44-1.
Because whole blood is rarely available, most women with obstetrical hemorrhage and ongoing massive blood loss are given packed red cells, crystalloid solutions, and blood components.
As subsequently discussed, many institutions use massive transfusion protocols (MTPs) designed to anticipate all facets of massive obstetrical hemorrhage.
These protocols commonly contain plasma, cryoprecipitate, and platelets in various ratios (Cunningham, 2015; Shields, 2011).
Table 44-1.
Blood Products Commonly Transfused in Obstetrical Hemorrhage Several studies have assessed plasma:red cell ratios with MTPs used in civilian trauma units and military combat hospitals (Hardin, 2014; Rahouma, 2018).
Patients receiving a massive transfusion—defined as 10 or more units of blood—had much higher survival rates as the ratio of plasma to red cell units neared 1:1.4, that is, one unit of plasma given for each 1.4 units of packed red cells.
By way of contrast, the highest mortality group had a ratio of 1:8.
From the foregoing, when red cell replacement exceeds five units or so, evaluation of platelet count, clotting studies, and plasma fibrinogen concentration is reasonable (Bienstock, 2021; Pacheco, 2019).
In the woman with obstetrical hemorrhage, the platelet count should be maintained >50,000/µL by the infusion of platelet concentrates.
A fibrinogen level <150 mg/dL or a sufficiently prolonged PT or PTT in a woman with surgical bleeding is an indication for replacement.
Fresh-frozen plasma is administered in doses of 10 to 15 mL/kg, or alternatively, cryoprecipitate is infused .
At Parkland Hospital, we use a standardized response to active hemorrhage.
If whole blood is not available, the following escalation of blood products is applied: 2 units packed red blood cells, and if continued bleeding, 2 units packed red blood cells and 2 units fresh-frozen plasma are automatically ordered.
Beyond this, MTP is initiated.
Whole Blood and Packed Red Blood Cells Compatible whole blood is ideal for management of severe obstetrical hemorrhage.
It has a shelf life of 40 days, and 70 percent of the transfused red cells function for at least 24 hours following transfusion.
One unit raises the hematocrit by 3 to 4 volume percent.
Important for obstetrical hemorrhage, whole blood replaces many coagulation factors needed in obstetrics—especially fibrinogen—and its plasma treats hypovolemia.
A collateral derivative is that women with severe hemorrhage are resuscitated with fewer blood
donor exposures than with packed red cells and components.
Experience at Parkland Hospital supports the preferable use of whole blood for massive hemorrhage (Alexander, 2009; Hernandez, 2012).
Of more than 66,000 deliveries, women with obstetrical hemorrhage treated with whole blood had significantly lower incidences of severe maternal morbidity that included renal failure, acute respiratory distress syndrome, pulmonary edema, hypofibrinogenemia, intensive care unit admissions, or maternal death compared with those given packed red cells and component therapy.
One unit of packed erythrocytes is derived from one unit of whole blood to have a hematocrit of 55 to 80 volume percent.
One unit will increase the hematocrit by 3 to 4 volume percent depending on the size of the woman.
Dilutional Coagulopathy A major drawback of massive hemorrhage treatment with crystalloid solutions and packed red blood cells is depletion of platelets and clotting factors.
Discussed later, this can lead to a dilutional coagulopathy that is clinically indistinguishable from DIC (Cunningham, 2015; Hossain, 2013).
Thrombocytopenia is the most frequent coagulation defect found with blood loss and multiple transfusions.
In addition, packed red cells have only very small amounts of soluble clotting factors, and stored whole blood is deficient in platelets and in factors V, VIII, and XI.
Thus, hypofibrinogenemia and prolongation of the prothrombin (PT) and partial thromboplastin times (PTT) are other sequelae.
Because many causes of obstetrical hemorrhage also cause DIC, the distinction between dilutional and consumptive coagulopathy can be confusing.
Fortunately, treatment for both is similar.
Platelets Platelet transfusions are considered with ongoing obstetrical hemorrhage if the platelet count falls below 50,000/µL .
In the nonsurgical patient, bleeding is rarely encountered if the platelet count is 10,000/µL or higher .
The preferable source of platelets is one “bag” obtained by single-donor apheresis.
This contains the equivalent of one unit each from six individual donors.
Depending on maternal size, each singledonor-apheresis, six-unit bag raises the platelet count by approximately 20,000/µL.
If these bags are not available, then individual-donor platelet units are used, and six to eight such units are generally transfused.
Importantly, the donor plasma in platelet units must be compatible with recipient erythrocytes.
Further, because some red blood cells are invariably transfused along with the platelets, only units from D-negative donors should be given to D-negative recipients.
Fresh-frozen Plasma This component is prepared by separating plasma from whole blood and then freezing it.
Approximately 30 minutes are required for frozen plasma to thaw.
It is a source of all stable and labile clotting factors, including fibrinogen.
Thus, it is often used for treatment of women with consumptive or dilutional coagulopathy.
Plasma is not a suitable volume expander in the absence of specific clotting factor deficiencies.
It is considered in a bleeding woman with a fibrinogen level <150 mg/dL or with an abnormal PT or PTT.
An alternative to frozen plasma is liquid plasma (LQP).
This neverfrozen plasma is stored at 1 to 60 C for up to 40 days, and its use compares favorably with fresh-frozen plasma .
Liquid plasma is not universally available in many centers.
Cryoprecipitate and Fibrinogen Concentrate Each unit of cryoprecipitate is prepared from one unit of fresh-frozen plasma.
Each 10- to 15-mL unit contains at least 200 mg of fibrinogen along with factor VIII:C, factor VIII:von Willebrand factor, factor XIII, and fibronectin .
It is usually given as a “pool” or “bag” using an aliquot of fibrinogen concentrate taken from 8 to 120 donors.
Cryoprecipitate is an ideal source of fibrinogen when levels are dangerously low and surgical incisions show oozing.
Because of transit time, the return of cryoprecipitate to transfusion services is often not feasible and is considered wastage if not deployed.
Nearly 17 percent of ordered
cryoprecipitate has been reported to be wasted in labor and delivery units, and this is the most commonly wasted product .
Another alternative is virus-inactivated fibrinogen concentrate .
These pooled fibrinogen products are marketed as RiaSTAP and Fibryna.
Each gram of concentrate raises the plasma fibrinogen level approximately 40 mg/dL.
These concentrates are used to treat congenital hypofibrinogenemia syndromes.
Recombinant Activated Factor VII This synthetic vitamin K–dependent protein is available as NovoSeven.
Recombinant activated factor VII (rFVIIa) binds to exposed tissue factor at the injury site to generate thrombin that activates platelets and the coagulation cascade.
Since its introduction, rFVIIa has been used to help control hemorrhage from surgery, trauma, and obstetrical causes (Goodnough, 2016; Murakami, 2015).
Many Level I trauma centers include it in MTPs. Importantly, rFVIIa will not be effective if the plasma fibrinogen level is <50 mg/dL or the platelet count is <30,000/µL.
One concern with rFVIIa is associated arterial—and to a lesser degree— venous thrombosis.
In a review of 35 randomized trials, arterial thromboembolism developed in 55 percent .
A second concern is that it has been found to have only marginal efficacy .
Tranexamic Acid Normally, plasminogen binds with tissue plasminogen activator (tPA) to form plasmin.
This binding degrades fibrin into fibrinogen–fibrin degradation products and leads to clot lysis.
Instead, tranexamic acid (TXA) reversibly binds to plasminogen, and thereby blocks plasmin binding to fibrin.
Fibrin strands are not broken, and a clot persists to slow down bleeding.
Ahmadzia and coworkers (2021) recently reported the pharmacodynamics of TXA at cesarean delivery using rotational thromboelastometry.
TXA inhibited tPA-induced clot lysis in a dosedependent manner.
In the randomized WOMAN trial of gravidas with hemorrhage following vaginal birth or during cesarean delivery, mortality rates from obstetrical hemorrhage were 1.2 percent in those given a 1-g intravenous TXA dose plus traditional care for bleeding.
This rate was statistically lower than the 1.7-percent death rate in women given traditional care alone .
The trial was carried out in developing nations and because of the results, the drug is recommended by the World Health Organization (2017).
In a large randomized trial of tranexamic acid given for prophylaxis, the drug did not decrease the rate of postpartum hemorrhage following vaginal delivery .
In the Tranexamic Acid for Preventing Postpartum Hemorrhage Following a Cesarean Delivery—TRAAP2 trial—women undergoing cesarean delivery who were given tranexamic acid prophylaxis had a lower incidence of redcell transfusions .
Gayet-Ageron and coworkers (2018) conducted a metaanalysis with more than 1000 patients with postpartum hemorrhage treated with TXA.
They also analyzed data from two randomized trials that included more than 40,000 women treated with TXA.
They concluded that treatment must be given soon after bleeding onset to reduce maternal mortality rates.
Shakur and colleagues (2018) performed a Cochrane database review and also concluded that early TXA administration decreases maternal deaths.
Most of these studies were conducted in impoverished countries, and the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2019a) does not recommend TXA for either prophylaxis or first-line treatment of obstetrical hemorrhage.
If used, administration within 3 hours of delivery is recommended.
Massive Transfusion Protocols As noted, these protocols are initiated once four to five units of packed red cells have been given within 2 hours or so.
These protocols speed blood product delivery to provide early resuscitation and help avoid dilutional coagulopathy.
Once activated, packed red cells, plasma, platelets, and fibrinogen are given set ratios .
Some protocols include rFVIIa, TXA, or prothrombin complex concentrates .
Table 44-2.
Parkland Hospital Obstetrical Massive Transfusion Protocol The data supporting the superiority of MTPs compared
with traditional component replacement to improve survival rates in obstetrical studies are limited.
Most reports describe nonpregnant trauma victims, but some observational studies address obstetrical hemorrhage (Green, 2016; Pacheco, 2016).
Viscoelastic Assays Thromboelastography (TEG) and rotational thromboelastometry (ROTEM) are point-of-care tests that assess coagulation in whole blood during massive transfusions.
These tests work by analyzing both clot formation and breakdown in a whole blood sample from a given patient.
Testing produces a profile of coagulation dynamics, and displayed values indicate the speed and quality of clot formation .
These assays provide information regarding time to clot formation, clot strength, and fibrinolysis .
Currently, they guide blood product replacement in trauma, liver transplant, and cardiac surgery patients.
Studies of TEG and ROTEM techniques in pregnant women have confirmed the hypercoagulable state of pregnancy and provide reference ranges for use in this population (Lee, 2021; McNamara, 2019; Pacheco, 2019).
Figure 44-1.
Normal thromboelastograph (TEG).
R (reaction time: start of test to clot forming.
K (clotting time): from start to 20 mm amplitude.
Alpha (α) angle: speed of fibrin formation.
A15, A20: amplitude at 15 and 20 minutes.
MCF: maximum clot firmness.
LY30: amount of clot lysed at 30 minutes.
Although promising, they also have several limitations.
For example, they are less informative in a woman with torrential hemorrhage in whom clotting function would need to be measured minute-by-minute.
They cannot be used to detect disorders of primary hemostasis .
A major drawback is the risk of misinterpretation when tests are used by inadequately trained personnel.
Although use is gaining favor, we and others recommend further study before these tests are widely applied for obstetrical hemorrhage treatment .
We have found this testing modality to be more applicable after initial management of hemorrhage and with intensive care recovery than during acute hemorrhage.
Cell Salvage and Autologous Transfusion Preoperative patient phlebotomy and autologous blood storage for transfusion in obstetrics has been disappointing.
Exceptions are women with a rare blood type or with unusual antibodies (Pacheco, 2013; Sullivan, 2019).
Intraoperative blood salvage with reinfusion is considered a safe intervention in obstetrical patients.
This practice may aid women declining transfusion .
Prior concern centered on amnionic fluid contamination and embolism (Dhariwal, 2014; Goucher, 2015).
To evaluate benefits, one trial randomly assigned 3028 women at risk for hemorrhage and undergoing cesarean delivery either to routine care or to cell salvage.
The rate of nonautologous donor blood transfusion was not significantly reduced in the cell salvage group—2.5 versus 3.5 percent .
In another study, Sullivan and colleagues (2019) routinely set up most cesarean deliveries for autologous transfusions and reported a lower rate of nonautologous donor transfusion.
Similar to prior reports, no cases of amnionic fluid embolism were reported in these two studies.
# Transfusion Complications.
Of serious known risks, transfusion of an incompatible blood component may result in acute hemolysis.
If severe, this can cause DIC, acute kidney injury, and death.
Preventable errors responsible for most of these reactions frequently include mislabeling of a specimen or incorrectly transfusing a patient not slated for those products.
The rate of such errors in the United States is estimated to be 1 case in 14,000 units, but these events are likely underreported .
A transfusion reaction is characterized by fever, hypotension, tachycardia, dyspnea, chest or back pain, flushing, severe anxiety, and hemoglobinuria.
Immediate supportive measures include stopping the transfusion, treating hypotension and hyperkalemia, provoking diuresis, and alkalinizing the urine.
Transfusion-related acute lung injury (TRALI) and transfusionassociated circulatory overload (TACO) are the most common causes of transfusion-related
mortality .
Affected women characteristically have severe dyspnea, hypoxia, and pulmonary edema that develop within 6 hours of transfusion .
Of the two, TACO is more common, and its incidence nears 1 percent.
TRALI is estimated to complicate at least 1 in 12,000 transfusions .
Although their pathogenesis is incompletely understood, injury to the pulmonary capillaries may arise from human leukocyte antigen (HLA) antibodies and human neutrophil antibodies (HNA) in donor plasma .
Management is supportive and may include mechanical ventilation .
Bacterial infection from transfusion of a contaminated blood component is unusual because organism growth is discouraged by refrigeration.
The most often implicated contaminants of red cells include Yersinia, Pseudomonas, Serratia, Acinetobacter, and Escherichia species.
The more important risk is from bacterial contamination of platelets, which are stored at room temperature.
Current estimates are that 1 in 1000 to 2000 platelet units are contaminated.
Death from transfusion-related sepsis is 1 case in 17,000 transfused single-donor platelets and 1 case in 61,000 transfused apheresis-donor packs .
Viral infection risks from transfusion have been curtailed.
The estimated risk of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or of hepatitis C virus infection in screened blood is 1 case in 1 to 2 million transfused units .
The estimated hepatitis B transmission rate is <1 case in 100,000 transfused units .
Because of the high prevalence of the virus, cytomegalovirus-infected leukocytes are often transfused.
Risks for transmitting West Nile virus, parvovirus B19, human Tlymphotropic virus type 1, and toxoplasmosis are slight (American Association of Blood Banks, 2013; Foroutan-Rad, 2016).
Although rare, Zika virus has emerged as another relevant transfusion-transmitted infection .
Collection of all whole blood components now includes testing for Zika virus .
At this time, transmission of SARS-CoV-2 virus from a COVID-positive donor is hypothetical .
Obstetrical Coagulopathies.
The terms consumptive coagulopathy, defibrination syndrome, and disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC) are often used interchangeably, but distinctions are important.
Actual consumption of procoagulants within the intravascular tree results in a consumptive coagulopathy.
In contrast, massive loss of procoagulants from hemorrhage results in a dilutional coagulopathy.
Semantics aside, consumptive coagulopathy culminates in a systemic intravascular activation that completely disrupts natural hemostasis.
As a result, an ineffective balance of natural anticoagulant mechanisms leads to widespread fibrin deposition that can cause multiorgan failure .
# Pregnancy-induced Coagulation Changes.
During normal pregnancy, the balance between coagulation and fibrinolysis changes to create a procoagulant state.
Changes that promote coagulation include appreciable elevation in the plasma concentrations of factors I (fibrinogen), VII, VII, IX, and X.
A partial list of these normal values is found in the Appendix (p. 1228).
Concurrently, levels of plasminogen, which lyses fibrin, rise considerably.
However, plasminogen activator inhibitor 1 and 2 (PAI-1 and PAI-2) levels also increase.
Thus, plasmin activity usually declines until after delivery (Hale, 2012; Hui, 2012).
As shown in Figure 47, (p. 62), mean platelet count drops by 10 percent during pregnancy, and platelet activation is enhanced (Kenny, 2015; Reese, 2018).
The net results of these changes include greater levels of fibrinopeptide A, β-thromboglobulin, platelet factor 4, and fibrinogen–fibrin degradation products, which includes D-dimers.
In addition to lower concentrations of the anticoagulant protein S, pregnancy-related hypercoagulability, and decreased fibrinolysis, there is augmented—yet compensated—intravascular coagulation that may function to maintain the uteroplacental interface.
# Disseminated Intravascular Coagulation.
Because of the many definitions and variable severity, the incidence of consumptive coagulopathy in gravidas varies and ranges from
0.03 to 0.35 percent (Erez, 2014; Rattray, 2012).
For example, some degree of significant coagulopathy is found in virtually all cases of placental abruption and amnionic fluid embolism.
Other instances in which frequently occurring but less recognized degrees of coagulation activation can be found include sepsis; thrombotic microangiopathies; acute kidney injury; acute fatty liver; severe preeclampsia; and hemolysis, elevated liver enzyme levels, low platelet count (HELLP) syndrome .
When consumptive coagulopathy is severe, the likelihood of maternal and perinatal morbidity and mortality rises.
In one study of 49 cases, antecedent causes included those listed above, and 59 percent received blood transfusions, 18 percent underwent hysterectomy, 6 percent required renal dialysis, and three mothers died .
In this series, the perinatal mortality rate was 30 percent.
From 2010 to 2011, DIC was the second most common severe maternal morbidity indicator .
DIC was associated with nearly a fourth of maternal deaths during this study period.
Despite these statistics, consumptive coagulopathy as the sole cause of maternal death is uncommon and accounts for only 0.2 percent of pregnancyrelated deaths in the United States .
# Activation of Normal Coagulation.
Instead of the “waterfall” sequential activation of the clotting cascade, a current theory proposes that tissue factor—an integral membrane glycoprotein—serves as the principal initiator of coagulation .
Coagulation then moves forward but incorporates a feedback loop.
To begin, tissue factor forms complexes with factor VII/VIIa to activate factors IX and X. Tissue factor is found in highly vascularized organs such as the brain, lungs, and placenta; in amnionic fluid; and in certain other cells (Kuczyfiski, 2002; Østerud, 2006; Uszyfiski, 2001).
Tissue factor–factor VIIa complexes ultimately generate activated factor X (Xa) to initiate clotting.
Subsequently, the previously labeled “intrinsic” pathway amplifies this process.
Specifically, the initial thrombin produced directly activates factor XI by providing a feedback amplification loop .
The end result of this amplified coagulation process is fibrin formation.
This is then counterbalanced by the fibrinolytic system, in which plasminogen is activated.
Even this process is tied initially to tissue factor.
The final product is fibrin degradation products, sometimes called fibrin split products, which include D-dimers.
Figure 44-2.
Coagulation pathway schematic.
FSP = fibrin split products; PAI = plasminogen activator inhibitor; TFPI = tissue factor pathway inhibitor.
# Activation of Pathological Coagulation.
With DIC, pathological entities prompt tissue factor release from subendothelial tissue and stimulated monocytes, which in turn provoke cytokine release from the endothelium.
With generalized endothelial activation, diffuse activation of coagulation follows.
This pathological cycle of coagulation and fibrinolysis becomes clinically important when coagulation factors and platelets are sufficiently depleted to create consumptive coagulopathy.
Purpura fulminans is a severe—often lethal—form of consumptive coagulopathy.
It is caused by microthrombi in small blood vessels leading to skin necrosis and sometimes vasculitis.
Debridement of large areas of skin over the extremities and buttocks frequently requires treatment in a burn unit.
Rarely, four-extremity amputation is required .
Purpura fulminans usually complicates sepsis in women with heterozygous protein C deficiencies and low protein C serum levels (Bhatti, 2019; Levi, 2016).
Importantly, homozygous protein C or S deficiency results in neonatal purpura fulminans, which is fatal .
# Inciting Conditions.
Several obstetrical syndromes can trigger consumptive coagulopathy.
Of these, placental abruption is the most common cause of severe consumptive coagulopathy in obstetrics and is discussed more fully in Chapter 43 (p. 749).
With preeclampsia, eclampsia, and HELLP syndrome, endothelial activation is a hallmark.
Perhaps 10 percent of HELLP cases have some
disseminated coagulation .
In general, the clinical severity of preeclampsia is directly correlated with thrombocytopenia and fibrin degradation products (Gedik 2017; Kenny, 2015).
That said, intravascular coagulation is seldom severe enough to be clinically worrisome .
Acute fatty liver of pregnancy also causes intravascular coagulation in addition to decreased procoagulant synthesis .
Amnionic fluid embolism is usually caused by intravenous embolization of meconium-laden amnionic fluid.
It results in rapid cardiorespiratory collapse and profound consumptive coagulopathy.
The Society for MaternalFetal Medicine (2021) has developed a checklist for the initial management of amnionic fluid embolism.
It is discussed in Chapter 42 (p. 745).
Sepsis stemming from various infections can be accompanied by endo-or exotoxin release.
Although a feature of sepsis syndrome includes activation of coagulation, seldom does sepsis alone cause massive procoagulant consumption.
Escherichia coli bacteremia is frequently seen with antepartum pyelonephritis and puerperal infections, however, accompanying consumptive coagulopathy is usually not severe.
Some notable exceptions are septicemia caused by exotoxins released from group A Streptococcus pyogenes, Staphylococcus aureus, or Clostridium perfringens, C sordellii, or C novyi (Herrera, 2016; Pritchard, 1971).
Treatment of sepsis and septic shock is discussed in Chapter 50 (p. 889).
Septic abortion—especially associated with these organisms—can incite coagulation and worsen hemorrhage.
Second-trimester induced abortions can stimulate intravascular coagulation even in the absence of sepsis.
Ben-Ami and associates (2012) described a 1.6-percent incidence in 1249 late-second-trimester pregnancies terminated by dilation and evacuation.
Two thirds were done for fetal demise, which may have contributed to coagulopathy .
Another source of intense coagulation is instillation of hypertonic solutions to effect midtrimester abortions.
These are not commonly used currently for pregnancy terminations.
The mechanism is thought to initiate coagulation by thromboplastin release into maternal circulation from the placenta, fetus, and decidua by the necrobiotic effect of hypertonic solutions.
Prolonged retention of a dead fetus is an unusual cause of consumptive coagulopathy today.
Namely, fetal death can be easily confirmed, and highly effective methods for labor induction are available.
Moreover, if the dead fetus is undelivered, most women enter spontaneous labor within 2 weeks and gross disruption of maternal coagulation rarely develops before 4 weeks (Pritchard, 1959, 1973).
After 1 month, however, almost a fourth will develop consumptive coagulopathy.
# Diagnosis.
Bioassay is an excellent method to detect or suspect clinically significant coagulopathy.
Excessive bleeding at sites of modest trauma characterizes defective hemostasis.
Examples include persistent bleeding from venipuncture sites, nicks from preoperative shaving, trauma from bladder catheterization, and spontaneous bleeding from the gums, nose, or gastrointestinal tract.
Purpura or petechiae at pressure sites such as sphygmomanometer cuffs or tourniquets suggest significant thrombocytopenia.
Any surgical procedure provides the ultimate bioassay and elicits generalized oozing from abdominal wall layers, the retroperitoneal space, the episiotomy, or incisions and dissections for cesarean delivery or hysterectomy.
Of laboratory tests, fibrinogen and D-dimer levels can be informative.
In late pregnancy, plasma fibrinogen levels typically have risen to 300 to 600 mg/dL.
Thus, even with severe consumptive coagulopathy, levels may sometimes be sufficiently high to protect against clinically harmful hypofibrinogenemia.
For example, defibrination caused by a placental abruption might lower an initial fibrinogen level of 600 mg/dL to 250 mg/dL.
Although this would indicate massive fibrinogen consumption, levels are still adequate to promote clinical coagulation.
The clinically impactful threshold usually approximates 150 mg/dL.
The effects of
serious hypofibrinogenemia —less than 50 mg/dL—can be illustrated with clinical thrombin clot test.
With low fibrinogen levels, the clot formed from whole blood in a glass phlebotomy tube will initially be soft and cannot retract in volume.
Instead, during the next half hour, platelet-induced clot retraction ensues, and this causes a tighter clot to form.
As depicted in Figure 44-2, fibrinolysis cleaves fibrin into various fibrin degradation products, and one of the smaller ones is the D-dimer.
Several sensitive assays contain monoclonal antibodies specific for D-dimers .
Assay values are almost always abnormally high with clinically significant consumptive coagulopathy.
At least in obstetrical disorders, quantification does not correlate with outcomes.
Examples of the magnitude of fibrin split product elevations in various obstetrical coagulopathies are shown in Figure 44-3.
Figure 44-3.
Quantification of fibrin split products in various obstetrical syndromes that cause disseminated intravascular coagulation.
AFLP = acute fatty liver of pregnancy; HELLP = hemolysis, elevated liver enzyme levels, low platelet count.
Reproduced with permission from Cunningham FG, Nelson DB: Disseminated intravascular coagulation syndromes in obstetrics.
Obstet Gynecol. 2015 Nov;126(5):999–1011) Thrombocytopenia is likely if petechiae are abundant or if clotted blood fails to retract within an hour or so.
Confirmation is provided by a low platelet count.
If severe preeclampsia syndrome is comorbid, qualitative platelet dysfunction may coexist .
Prothrombin time (PT) and partial thromboplastin time (PTT) are standard coagulation tests.
Prolongation may stem from very low fibrinogen concentrations, from appreciably reduced levels of the procoagulants needed to generate thrombin, or from large amounts of circulating fibrinogen–fibrin degradation products.
Thromboelastometry and thromboelastography are point-of-care tests used as adjuncts to conventional laboratory studies (McNamara, 2019; Pacheco, 2019).
Their current role may serve to guide blood product replacements as discussed earlier (p. 774).
Using many of these tests, several organizations have attempted to establish a more uniform definition of DIC.
One is the International Society on Thrombosis and Haemostasis (ISTH) scoring system.
The score is used only after a condition known to cause intravascular coagulation is identified and is calculated using a combination of laboratory tests.
Composite ISTH-DIC scores <5 suggest nonovert DIC, whereas scores ≥5 are compatible with overt DIC.
A scoring system for nonovert DIC has been developed by Alhousseini and coworkers (2020).
These scoring systems have not been applied widely in obstetrics (Hizkiyahu, 2019; Jonard, 2016; Nelson, 2014).
# General Management.
To halt ongoing defibrination, identifying and removing the inciting source is a priority.
With incisions or extensive lacerations accompanied by severe hemorrhage, rapid replacement of procoagulants is usually indicated.
Vigorous restoration and maintenance of the circulation to treat hypovolemia cannot be overemphasized.
Adequate perfusion restores hepatic and endothelial synthesis of procoagulants and permits prompt removal of activated coagulation factors, fibrin, and fibrin degradation products by the reticuloendothelial system.
Aside from these fundamental steps, few other agents have proved soundly effective.
Although its use is seemingly counterintuitive, unfractionated heparin has now been abandoned.
Other agents not recommended for first-line use include tranexamic acid or epsilonaminocaproic acid, both antifibrinolytic agents (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2019a; Pacheco, 2017).
This is because the fibrinolytic system is necessary for dissolution of widespread fibrin thromboses caused by generalized intravascular coagulation .
Discussed earlier (p. 773), recombinant factor VIIa (rFVIIa) can be used to help control severe obstetrical hemorrhage from other causes.
However, current clinical evidence is insufficient to make firm
recommendations on its administration for obstetrical coagulopathies.
Surgical Management Of Hemorrhage.
Several invasive procedures can help to arrest severe postpartum hemorrhage.
A report from the Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality concluded that most studies addressing these methods are of poor quality .
In one study of 6660 women with postpartum hemorrhage, 4 percent underwent an invasive procedure, and 1 percent had a hysterectomy .
The failure rate of conservative surgical and embolization procedures was 15 percent.
Of specific methods, use of uterine balloon tamponade for treatment of atony has doubled in the past decade (Merriam, 2020; Suarez, 2020).
It is described in Chapter 42 (p. 737).
For low-pressure bleeding, topical hemostatic agents can be used to control persistent surgical oozing.
These were reviewed by Stachowicz and colleagues (2020).
Other than for cesarean hysterectomy, these are seldom used in obstetrical hemorrhage.
# Uterine Compression Sutures.
This surgical technique uses a no. 2 chromic suture to compress the anterior and posterior uterine walls together .
Because they give the appearance of suspenders, they are also called braces .
Several modifications of the B-Lynch technique have been described (Gilmandyar, 2019; Matsubara, 2013; Nelson, 2007).
Figure 44-4.
Uterine compression suture or “brace.
The B-Lynch suture technique is illustrated from an anterior view of the uterus in Figures A, B, and D and a posterior view in Figure C.
The numbers denote the sequential path of the suture and are shown in more than one figure.
Step 1.
Beginning below the incision, the needle pierces the lower uterine segment to enter the uterine cavity.
Step 2.
The needle exits the cavity above the incision.
The suture then loops up and around the fundus to the posterior uterine surface.
Step 3.
The needle pierces the posterior uterine wall to reenter the uterine cavity.
The suture then traverses to the opposite side within the cavity.
Step 4.
The needle exits the uterine cavity through the posterior uterine wall.
From the back of the uterus, the suture loops up and around the fundus to the front of the uterus.
Step 5.
The needle pierces the myometrium above the incision to reenter the uterine cavity.
Step 6.
The needle exits below the incision, and the sutures at points 1 and 6 are tied below the incision.
The hysterotomy incision is then closed in the usual fashion.
B-Lynch sutures are mainly used to treat atony.
These may help diminish DIC-associated bleeding, while coagulation is corrected by transfusion.
Success rates vary by indication.
For example, B-Lynch (2005) cited 948 cases with only 7 failures.
Conversely, in other series, overall failure rates were 20 to 25 percent (Kaya, 2016; Kayem, 2011).
Some unique complications can rarely follow compression sutures .
Most involve variations of uterine ischemic necrosis with peritonitis (Gottlieb, 2008; Joshi, 2004; Treloar, 2006).
In most cases, subsequent pregnancies are uneventful if compression sutures are used .
A few women with B-Lynch sutures, however, developed uterine wall defects or uterine cavity synechiae (Akoury, 2008; Alouini, 2011; Ibrahim, 2013).
# Artery Ligation.
Ligation of arterial blood flow to the uterus can halt or diminish obstetrical hemorrhage.
Common indications include uterine hysterotomy incision laceration, uterine atony, and abnormal placentation.
Uterine artery ligation may be unilateral or bilateral and is used mainly for lacerations at the lateral part of a hysterotomy incision .
In our experiences, this procedure is less helpful for other hemorrhage etiologies.
In rare cases with torrential hemorrhage from placenta accreta syndrome, a tourniquet wrapped around the lower uterine segment may slow bleeding sufficiently while resuscitation ensues and dissection for hysterectomy is performed.
Figure 44-5.
Uterine artery ligation.
The suture goes through the lateral uterine wall anteriorly, curves posteriorly, and then re-enters anteriorly.
When tied, it encompasses the uterine artery.
Internal iliac artery ligation
may also be unilateral or bilateral.
For years, ligation has been used to reduce pelvic hemorrhage.
However, the procedure may be technically difficult and is successful in only half of cases (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2019a; Bienstock, 2021).
Wei and colleagues (2019) reported it to be successful for improved hemostasis with placenta previa.
It is not particularly helpful for abating hemorrhage with postpartum atony .
For internal iliac ligation, adequate exposure is obtained by opening the peritoneum over the common iliac artery and dissecting down to the bifurcation of the external and internal iliac arteries .
Branches distal to the external iliac arteries are palpated to verify pulsations at or below the inguinal area.
Ligation of the internal iliac artery at a point 5 cm distal to the common iliac bifurcation will usually avoid the internal iliac artery’s posterior division branches .
The areolar sheath of the artery is incised longitudinally, and a right-angle clamp is carefully passed just beneath the artery from lateral to medial.
Care must be taken not to perforate contiguous large veins, especially the internal iliac vein.
Suture— usually nonabsorbable—is passed under the artery with a clamp, and the vessel is then securely ligated.
Figure 44-6.
Ligation of the right internal iliac artery.
Unembalmed cadaveric dissection shows the right-angle clamp passing underneath the anterior division of the internal iliac artery just distal to its posterior division.
Reproduced with permission from Dr. Marlene Corton.
The most important mechanism of action with internal iliac artery ligation is an 85-percent reduction in pulse pressure in those arteries distal to the ligation .
This converts an arterial pressure system into one with pressures approaching those in the venous circulation.
This creates vessels more amenable to hemostasis via pressure and clot formation.
Even bilateral internal iliac artery ligation does not appear to interfere with subsequent reproduction.
Nizard and colleagues (2003) reported subsequent pregnancy in 17 such women.
From a total of 21 pregnancies, 13 were normal, 3 ended with miscarriage, 3 were terminated, and 2 were ectopic.
# Angiographic Embolization.
This modality is now used for many causes of intractable hemorrhage when surgical access is difficult.
Its use has increased remarkably in the past decade .
In more than 500 pregnancy-related cases, embolization was effective in 90 percent (Grönvall, 2014; Lee, 2012; Poujade, 2011; Zhang, 2015).
After his review, Rouse (2013) concluded that embolization can be used to arrest refractory postpartum hemorrhage.
Other reports have been less enthusiastic.
Fertility is not impaired, and many subsequent successful pregnancies have been reported (Fiori, 2009; Kolomeyevskaya, 2009).
An important caveat for these procedures is that women with hemodynamic instability related to active bleeding should not be removed from the operating room.
Complications are relatively uncommon but can be severe.
Case reports detail instances of iatrogenic iliac artery rupture, uterine ischemic necrosis, and uterine infection (Grönvall, 2014; Katakam, 2009; Nakash, 2012).
A rare case of massive buttock necrosis and paraplegia followed bilateral internal iliac artery embolization .
A myometrial defect in subsequent pregnancy also has been reported .
In a few instances, massive blood loss and difficult surgical dissection is anticipated.
The use of balloon-tipped catheters preoperatively inserted into the iliac or uterine arteries is described in management of placenta accreta spectrum .
# Aortic Compression.
Prophylactic use of an aortic balloon occlusion device has been reported to reduce blood loss and the need for hysterectomy .
Also known as resuscitative endovascular balloon occlusion of the aorta (REBOA), such occlusion lowers the perfusion pressure distally, increases cardiac afterload, and redistributes blood volume to the heart and brain .
Prolonged occlusion can result in lower limb ischemia requiring amputation.
Whittington and colleagues (2020) described its successful prophylactic use in 11 women with placenta accreta spectrum disorders.
Instead, manual compression of the aorta above the sacral promontory can be used in cases in which pelvic hemorrhage is torrential.
If the abdomen is closed, pressure placed above the umbilicus reduces blood pressure distally .
# Pelvic Packing.
If hysterectomy fails to curtail hemorrhage, then pelvic packing with gauze and termination of the operation may be considered (Pacheo, 2018; Touhami, 2018).
Rolls of gauze are packed to provide constant local pressure.
In some cases, this may serve as a temporizing step prior to interventional embolization.
In other cases, packing alone may be left for 48 to 72 hours.
If the patient is stable and bleeding appears to have stopped, packing is removed.
In one review of 104 cases, the success rate was 79 percent.
Packing failed in 24 patients, and 13 of these women died, yielding an overall mortality rate of 13 percent .
The umbrella or parachute pack uses a similar concept .
Although seldom used today, it can be lifesaving if all other measures have failed, especially in low-resource areas (Dildy, 2006; Touhami, 2018).
The pack is constructed of a sturdy sterile plastic bag that is filled with gauze rolls that are unwound and knotted together.
Sufficient rolls are used to provide adequate volume in the bag to fill the pelvis.
The pack is introduced transabdominally with the stalk exiting the vagina.
Mild traction is applied by tying the stalk to a 1-liter fluid bag, which is hung over the foot of the bed.
The umbrella pack is removed vaginally after 24 hours.